Ratnadeep Mitra

Washington, D.C.

((202) 515-0174

in linkedin.com/in/ratnadeep-mitra/

CORE COMPETENCIES

Data Mining/Processing, Statistical and Predictive Analysis, Machine Learning, Data Visualization, Natural Language Processing

TECHNICAL EXPERTISE

Languages:

• R, Python, SQL, Scala

Tools and Frameworks:

Tableau, AWS, Spark, Hadoop, Keras

Others

 Web Development, C#, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Agile Scrum

CERTIFICATIONS

- Data Scientist with R Language (Simplilearn, July 2016)
- Oracle Database SQL Certified Expert (Oracle, July 2013)

COURSE PROJECTS

- Sarcasm Detection
 - Used RNN and LSTM network
 - Achieved 84% accuracy
- Document Summarization
 - Used Seq2Seq model with GRU encoder and decoder
 - For training, team used news articles from 15 American publications.
- Economy of Sub-Saharan Africa: A Visual Exploration
 - For creating visuals, team used R, Python, Tableau and Shiny
 - Collaborated with QED Group
 - Visualizations created are featured on QED Group's website
- The Relationship between Weather and People's Sentiment
 - For analysis, team used reviews from Yelp and weather data
 - Focused on sentiment analysis, topic modeling, network analysis and unsupervised machine learning

PORTFOLIO

- https://github.com/ratnadeepmitra
- https://ratnadeepmitra.github.io/

SUMMARY

Motivated **Data Scientist** with strong background in software development and experience in data processing and data mining algorithms and dashboard development to solve challenging business problems and deliver valuable insights. Continuous learner and passionate about natural language processing and data visualization.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Sep 2018 - Data Scientist Consultant

Present

The World Bank

- Part of the Development Economics (DEC) Data Group
- Automate UIS statistical data and metadata collection and preparation of data for analysis to allow developers and researchers to build websites and applications
- Responsible for analyzing international poverty data
- Communicate findings, recommendations, and opportunities to team improve data systems
- Develop wrapper functions in R for PovcalNet application to abstract complex calculation

Jun 2018 -Aug 2018

Research Intern

Hanover Research

- Applied extensive data cleaning operation, and developed automation scripts in R to analyze massive survey data
- Implemented advanced data mining algorithms and topic modeling on survey responses to identify consumer preferences
- Built executive dashboards to discover industry trends using Tableau
- Developed web scrapers to collect raw data from the web
- Assisted the VP in competitor analysis with insightful visualizations using Amazon Alexa API and R

Aug 2013 -Jun 2017

Senior Software Engineer

First American (India) Pvt. Ltd.

- 1 of 5 employees out of 700+ to win 'Top Performer' award for exceptional performance in 2016 2nd quarter
- Developed and administrated SQL database to analyze employees' competencies to aid team building and hiring process
- Contributed software engineering expertise in a client-facing role in the development of web interfaces and APIs
- Spearheaded project to develop a tool to facilitate cross-selling
- Mentored fresh graduates joining the organization

EDUCATION

Aug 2017 -

M.S. in Analytics (Concentration in Data Science)

May 2019

Georgetown University GPA: 3.75 / 4 (as of Fall 2018)

Aug 2009 -Jun 2013 **B.Tech.** in Electronics and Communication Engineering

West Bengal University of Technology

GPA: 8.36 / 10 (equivalent to 3.76 / 4, as evaluated by WES)

OTHER EXPERIENCE

- Mentor for Georgetown Graduate Analytics Program Fall 2018 cohort
- Speaker at Georgetown Graduate Analytics Student Internship Experience Seminar
- **Database Specialist** for Georgetown Graduate Analytics Program
- Graduate Teaching Assistant for Data Visualization, Introduction to Information Technology and Advanced Programming Topics